<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Danny Navarro's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-11T17:25:58+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://dannynavarro.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Danny Navarro]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[j@dannynavarro.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/2011/09/20/migrating-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-20T19:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://dannynavarro.net/2011/09/20/migrating-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally found some time to migrate my blog to <a href="http://wordpress.com/">Octopress</a> from
<a href="http://octopress.org/">Wordpress.com</a>. The critical reason to migrate from Wordpress has
been the support for nice code syntax highlighting, something I
couldn&rsquo;t have wordpress.com, at least for free. I know there are very
nice wordpress plugins for syntax highlighting but in order to use
them I would have to host it myself. I don&rsquo;t want to go through the
hassle of maintaining a typical PHP/MySQL stack or to be worried about
being <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slashdotted"><em>slashdotted</em></a>.</p>

<p>Having worked with an excellent documentation tool like <a href="http://sphinx.pocoo.org/">Sphinx</a>, I
started looking to static blog generators meant. It turned out that
<a href="http://blog.manuelviera.es/">Manu Viera</a>, a colleague working at <a href="http://www.yaco.es/">Yaco</a> with me, shared the
same itch and had already looked several static web generators in
Python, which is our main language at <a href="http://www.yaco.es/">Yaco</a>. Manu found
<a href="https://github.com/ametaireau/pelican">pelican</a> the best candidate but still I found it a bit immature,
not something like something like <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>.</p>

<p>Then I found <a href="http://wordpress.com/">Octopress</a>, a framework built on top of <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>
with <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/plugins/">several plugins</a>, including syntax highlighting or automatic
support for <a href="http://disqus.com/">disqus</a> comments.</p>

<p>The migration from wordpress was not too painful. I used the default
Jekyll script to import wordpress posts and disqus importer for the
comments.  After some sed commands I got nice markdown formatted
scripts.</p>

<p>I had some trouble in the beginning configuring an isolated Ruby
runtime in <a href="http://archlinux.org/">Arch Linux</a> just for Octopress but after discovering
<a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv">rbenv</a>, everything went smooth. (I prefer rbenv instead RVM with
rbenv I know at any moment what it&rsquo;s doing).</p>

<p>Deploying an Octopress generated site to <a href="http://pages.github.com/">github pages</a> is as
<a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/index.html">easy</a> as pie.</p>

<p>Aside of nice Python syntax highlighting now I have some extra
advantages I didn&rsquo;t have with wordpress.com:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Markdown syntax when writing my posts.</p></li>
<li><p>I can use the best text editor to mankind: <a href="http://www.vim.org/">vim</a> :P</p></li>
<li><p>My blog data becomes more manageable. If at some point I don&rsquo;t want
to host it github, I could just to push it somewhere else with no
modification.</p></li>
<li><p>I got a very nice default theme for free, that aside of looking
good, it&rsquo;s also very easy to tweak and maintain.</p></li>
<li><p>Now I have a good excuse to learn Ruby outside of RoR influence.
Ruby is one of those languages I wish I would be better at, even if
Python remains my main working language.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>In any case, I must say the service provided by wordpress.com has been
quite good but this one of those cases where you have to say: <em>“Sorry,
it&rsquo;s not you, it&rsquo;s just me”.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The blogging itch]]></title>
    <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/2010/03/24/the-blogging-itch/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dannynavarro.net/2010/03/24/the-blogging-itch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a blog has been in my personal todo list for years. Finally, after encouraging myself with <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2006/03/users-dont-care-about-you.html">some</a> <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/10/how-to-achieve-ultimate-blog-success-in-one-easy-step.html">old</a> <a title="post" href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2006/02/fear-of-writing.html" target="_self">posts</a> from Jeff Atwood (yeah, I like reading <a title="Jeff Atwood" href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/" target="_self">Jeff Atwood</a> and I frequently agree with him), I decided to just kicked it off with whatever I have in my mind: why it has been so difficult to get started? Why now? It was not only procrastination, there has been something else. Let me explain.</p>

<p>I started using routinely a feed reader around 4 years ago. Since then I&rsquo;ve been constantly replacing the blog feeds I follow with others I found more interesting. Right now all the blogs I&rsquo;m following are excellently written, and I&rsquo;m not talking only about celebrity blogs, but also the kind of highly technical blogs that make it, for example, into <a href="http://planet.python.org/">Python planet</a>. When I think about the quality of writing I would like for my blog several blogs from Python planet come to my mind. But even if I put myself a much lower quality threshold to get started, it turns out that writing something of acceptable quality, just the writing, is indeed harder than it seems. I can <a href="http://zenhabits.net/2009/04/seven-productivity-tips-for-people-that-hate-gtd/" target="_self">allow myself to suck</a> but can&rsquo;t go public with something I know is total crap. Recently I reached a writing level where I&rsquo;m comfortable enough to go public.</p>

<p>But obviously publishing a decent blog is not only about writing properly. You need something to write about. For me it&rsquo;s not worth writing superficially just for the sake of writing. In order to comment on something I need to have a deep understanding of the matter, otherwise I can&rsquo;t confidently give a public opinion. But for that to happen I need something I didn&rsquo;t get until recently: specialized knowledge.</p>

<p>When I started my Biochemistry degree back in Spain I liked computers as a hobby  (I was a relatively early Linux user) but my real passion was molecular biology, the wet lab. Soon I realized how much tedious manual work and luck influenced in successful biological experiments. In the other hand, <em>experiments</em> using the computer were quick and you could somehow understand much better what was going on.</p>

<p>Later I worked for <a href="http://pandeylab.igm.jhmi.edu/akhilesh.html">Akhilesh Pandey</a> developing <a href="http://hprd.org/">HPRD</a>, a human protein database that included (and still does) plenty of high quality manually curated from scientific literature not found in any other biological databases. My role was a kind of bridge between the programmers, the curators and the biological requirements for the project. My research career started totally different to what it&rsquo;s expected from a young researcher, instead of specializing in something first and from there try to understand later how what you study contributes to science in general, I had to first understand the global picture before trying to get into the nitty-gritty. That didn&rsquo;t mean I didn&rsquo;t want to get deep into different areas. The problem was that I wanted to get into too many things at the same time. After some time the fields where I really ended up focusing have become fewer. Now, instead of working in large teams, I work more isolated in a very specialized projects within the area of proteomics informatics.</p>

<p>Then if finally I ended up working in a very specialized topic was the global view experience a waste of time? Absolutely not. My way of thinking has been critically shaped since then. I&rsquo;m the kind of person who has to have a clear reason of everything I do. Now it&rsquo;s clear for me on what I want to focus on, without losing the context of everything I do. I know what I want to learn and for what. I still maintain more or less the same goals that I had when I got into research, the difference now is how I want to reach those goals. But I&rsquo;ll leave my goals for another post.</p>

<p>In the end the lack of specialized knowledge has been a important blocker to start a blog. I didn&rsquo;t feel with enough authority to write acceptable posts for concrete topics. Now in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Python_(programming_language)">Python</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proteomics">proteomics</a> I&rsquo;m more or less getting above the knowledge threshold where I can start writing something critically.</p>

<p>At the same type proteomics informatics is a blend of very different specialized topics. In proteomics I still don&rsquo;t totally understand how a <a href="http://www.chemguide.co.uk/analysis/masspec/howitworks.html">mass spectrometer</a> works but of so much parsing, merging, querying, filtering, and plotting mass spec data I got a good handle of what mass spec proteomics data is like. About programming I&rsquo;m far from writing something I would qualify as <em>good code</em>. Even if my coding capabilities have improved over the years I qualify my code worse than I used to. In reality my code is better now, it&rsquo;s just that, with time, I&rsquo;m becoming more critical about what I would call good code. However I&rsquo;m fully aware that being so critical with my own code is a <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2009/07/nobody-hates-software-more-than-software-developers.html">symptom of programming competence</a>. I feel I&rsquo;m on the right track, if I keep pushing like I&rsquo;m doing I&rsquo;ll eventually get to write something I could qualify as good enough. For now I feel competent enough in Python to start saying something meaningful about programming publicly.</p>

<p>The bottom line is that now I have some specific knowledge and a decent ability for writing. One would think that these factors provide the ideal scenario to start a blog. I know that having a blog is very important for my profession but that hasn&rsquo;t be the last push to start now. I&rsquo;m writing this post right now because I need it. Let me rephrase it: I&rsquo;m not forcing myself to write a blot, I need to write.</p>

<p>What is really happening is that blogging is just part of a bigger transformation I&rsquo;m going through. I&rsquo;ve been lurking for quite some time different open source communities, initially just to learn more from people who are way better than me in programming. But lately I have been developing a great admiration for certain communities and  individuals. I need to give them something back. I&rsquo;m gradually participating more in the community. Now I need show who I am, how I see the world, what I want in life and what do I admire and why.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;m blogging.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
