<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: history | Danny Navarro's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/categories/history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-08T14:20:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://dannynavarro.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Danny Navarro]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[j@dannynavarro.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Podcast tribute]]></title>
    <link href="http://dannynavarro.net/2014/03/26/podcast-tribute/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-26T20:53:58+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://dannynavarro.net/2014/03/26/podcast-tribute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These days, with the pervasiveness of the Internet, an impressive wave of
new spoken audio content is making steadily its way into the mainstream.
I&rsquo;ve always been a big fan of spoken radio, but now I find myself
listening only to independent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podcast">podcasts</a>, mostly hosted by
amateurs, who are able to provide fresh and genuine content in a medium
where innovation has been stagnant for many years.</p>

<p>The least I can do for all the countless hours of entertainment they are
giving me is to publicly express my admiration for them.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.dancarlin.com/disp.php/hh">Hardcore History</a></h4>

<p>When a new episode of this podcast comes out I try to wrap up everything
I&rsquo;m doing and take a hiking route with my dog long enough to listen to the
new episode uninterrupted. I think what makes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Carlin">Dan Carlin</a> outstanding as
a narrator is his great ability to immerse the listener in the situation
of the era and to describe how it felt to be in the shoes of the people
living through it. All in all, after listening to several episodes, I came
to realize we are not so different from our ancestors, and in most cases,
no matter how horrible the consequences of some actions were, we&rsquo;d
probably have done the same.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.histocast.com">HistoCast (Spanish)</a></h4>

<p>This history podcast is carried in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tertulia"><em>tertulia</em></a> format by a panel of
history aficionados. The general tone is informal but at the same time
it&rsquo;s quite rigorous regarding the information they provide and throughout
in their analysis. The anecdotes they manage to find are priceless.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.colectivoburbuja.org/">Colectivo Burbuja (Spanish)</a></h4>

<p>When living in a country like <a href="http://www.heritage.org/index/country/spain">Spain</a>, with a government filled with
corrupted crooks who control practically all traditional media outlets,
independent podcasts like this one are really appreciated. It mostly
consists of debates with speakers of diverse ideologies analyzing current
news, mainly economic. It really helps understand what is really going on
in this country, full of strange contradictions.</p>

<h4><a href="https://www.grc.com/securitynow.htm">Security Now</a></h4>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Gibson_(computer_programmer)">Steve Gibson</a> could be accused of being an expert in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_relations">PR</a> more than an
expert in information security but, in spite of this, I find hard to deny
his didactic ability to introduce the listener to different security
concepts and to summarize the most important security events of the week.</p>

<h4><a href="http://sixgun.org/linuxoutlaws">Linux Outlaws</a></h4>

<p>By the title one would expect a highly technical podcast, but more than
a podcast about the Linux world, this is about using Linux as a excuse for
numerous ranting, cynical comments and nerdy jokes, which I find really
funny.</p>

<h4><a href="http://12byzantinerulers.com/">12 Byzantine Rulers</a> and <a href="http://normancenturies.com/">Norman Centuries</a></h4>

<p>Even if they are considered podcasts, they feel more like history
audiobooks. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lars_brownworth">Lars Brownworth</a> fabulously narrates relatively unknown
amazing epochs which were highly influential but didn&rsquo;t get the historical
popularity they deserved.</p>

<h4><a href="http://podcasts.joerogan.net/">The Joe Rogan Experience</a></h4>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Rogan">Joe Rogan</a> interviews in a funny and informal tone diverse personalities.
I view these discussions as examples of honest civilized conversations
between individuals with very different backgrounds. I also found very
interesting podcasters through this podcast.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.haskellcast.com/">The HaskellCast</a></h4>

<p>Because these days I&rsquo;m coding full-time in <a href="http://www.haskell.org/">Haskell</a>, in this podcast, I
really appreciate the interviews to prominent figures in the community.
What I like the most about listening to them instead of just reading what
they write, is that somehow, by hearing them explain what they do, it&rsquo;s
easier to grasp the train of thought that led them to do what they did.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.revolutionspodcast.com/">Revolutions</a></h4>

<p>This history podcast is very informationally dense but fun to listen to
nevertheless. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Duncan_(podcaster)">Mike Duncan</a> does a great job explaining the high
complexity of events that led to big changes in history. He&rsquo;s also the
author of <a href="http://thehistoryofrome.typepad.com/">History of Rome</a> which I still haven&rsquo;t gone through but hope to
start doing it that at some point.</p>

<h4><a href="http://pasajesdelahistoria.ueuo.com/">Pasajes de la Historia (Spanish)</a></h4>

<p>This is one of the few podcasts I listen that it&rsquo;s taken from traditional
media. Unfortunately, <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Antonio_Cebri%C3%A1n">Juan Antonio Cebrián</a> passed away prematurely but
left an incredible legacy in the form of tales based on historical
figures.</p>

<h4><a href="http://letstalkbitcoin.com/">Let&rsquo;s talk Bitcoin</a></h4>

<p>This is also a podcast I follow for professional reasons. If I had to
choose a single <a href="https://bitcoin.org/">Bitcoin</a> podcast this would be the one.</p>

<!---
vim: tw=74 spell
-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
